Hello everyone. My name is Greg and I
dev stuff. Welcome everyone to episode
six of the tactics game in Unity. In
this episode we will import the
character model and build the animator
controller for this character.
So today we are going to learn how to
use animator controller and import this
beautiful model done by Declan Mohan.
His Discord and contacts in the
description.
And you can get this model with
animations absolutely for free in the
description. You can use this model and
animations in your project. You are not
allowed to redistribute or resell this
model. You only allowed to ship this
model as part of your game.
After downloading the package, unpack
the zip archive and import everything
that is inside this zip archive into the
project.
This kind of asset is made possible by
support of people on Patreon and members
on YouTube. If you want to see more
assets and me doing this job full-time,
you can support me on Patreon or on
YouTube and get rewards like project
files and be shown on the screen right
now. Thank you very much.
Good. Now you have all those files.
Before we begin animating, we need to
build the character on the scene. Let's
make separate scene. Let's call it an
animation test scene.
So, now I want to bring your attention
to the bottom left corner.
From now on, at the beginning of the
each tutorial, you will see the latest
version of the models package.
Inside your package you will have a
notepad file with the current version of
the package and some additional
information.
If your version is lower than the
version shown on the screen, I advise
you immediately look into description
and download latest version of the
package.
To update the package,
simply unpack the package into the asset
folder.
To keep all the assets consistent, keep
all asset I gave you in this folder.
This way assets will be able to
overwrite changes automatically.
Remember, updates might overwrite
something and break animations or
prefabs or some other stuff.
Drop the character model and weapon
model on the scene.
Now let's build the material for the
character.
Select the armor mesh
and drag and drop the armor texture.
Then we want to add the occlusion map
onto the material.
Good.
Do the same for the base mesh.
Now set the sword in the same fashion.
Now we want to build an animator
controller. An animator controller allow
you to arrange and maintain a set of
animation clips and associated animation
transition for a character or object.
The animator controller has references
to the animation clips used within it
and manages the various animation clips
and the transitions between them using a
state machine.
Which could be thought of of as a
flowchart of animation clips and
transitions which tells what kind of
animation your model should be playing.
Small warning. In later version names of
the animations or the
or the place where they are stored might
change. Don't be scared. The main naming
convention will stay the same. Check the
included notepad for additional
information. Use search or join the
discord to seek help.
Select the animation. To make it easier
to read the names of the animation, I
change the view of the project by
holding the control and using scroll on
mouse.
Select the two-handed idle animation.
Drag it into the inspector of the knight
character main object. This will create
an animator controller which will lead
into the idle immediately.
To see that, double click into the
controller.
To see the model better, let's move the
camera.
If I launch the game, the animation will
only loop once. So, we need to tell to
the game that this animation should be
looping. To do that, select the file
with animation in the project. Find the
idle animation and click on loop time.
Do the same for run. Any animations
which will be looped need to be marked
as loopable.
Apply the changes.
Good. Now the idle animation looping
well.
Now we want to introduce a transition to
the run and from the idle and run to the
attack.
Create states for 200 attack and 200
run.
Make transition
between them by pressing right mouse
button and pressing make transition.
Good, but we need to control those
transitions. We need to have a set of
parameters to tell to our model when
this model is supposed to run, when this
model is supposed to attack, or when
this model does nothing and idle.
Create two bool parameters, one for move
and one for attack.
Now in transition, we need to tell that
when the move is true, then we run.
If it's not, return to the idle state.
On the transition between idle and
attack, when we transition into attack,
make condition if attack is true.
But on the exit out of attack, we want
to specify besides the attack being
false, that move is false, too.
Because attack can transition into
moving, too.
Now if I will manipulate the parameters,
you will see is it our character will
move and will attack. But it feels
awkward, like it takes some time for
animator to catch up with the
parameters.
This is happening because animation
state wants to finish playing the
animation before transitioning to new
state.
To avoid this, we need to turn off the
has exit time parameter.
You have to do this for each transition
which you want to start transitioning
the moment the condition is met.
Good. Now let's put the sword into the
hands. To do that, we need to place a
sword into what is called leading bone,
which is right now called sword def air.
Also, there is an error with the rig.
The rotation had to be modified to be
placed correctly in two hands. Add minus
90° into X rotation. If you are from the
future and sword is already placed well
in two hands, you don't have to change
anything.
We are done with the animator controller
and setting up the rig. We will be
actually using this model and animation
in the next episode.
Good, this is it for this episode. If
you have any questions or any ideas
about code, please leave your comment
below. If you're interested in seeing
what will come out of this, please
subscribe. If you want to support
further, you can find my Patreon in the
description. Special thank you to Andrew
Be Long and ThisOldHatch Do for their
generous support. With best regards, see
you in the next episode.